ALLOYS NICHOLAS ODHIAMBO SIAYA

B.SC, MBA, PRINCE2, ITIL, SAP, UNIX

Address: P.O. Box 61952 - 00200, NAIROBI, KENYA.

Telephone: +254(722)787 302 Email: alloys.siaya@gmail.com

CAREER PROFILE

I am a respected, well-accomplished **ICT Professional** with excellent organizational skills. I have managed many automation projects and developed and managed highly effective ICT services teams in the support of business. I consistently demonstrate the ability to meet managerial and technical automation requirements and to satisfy customer needs. My illustrious career has spanned systems development, project management, service delivery, strategy and governance.

I am an effective **communicator and relationship builder** with superior detail orientation. I engender collaborative spirit across all management, department, and functional levels while consistently gaining the confidence and support of seniors, peers and subordinates.

I have over 20+ years of successful IT systems implementations and effective services delivery, resulting in business growth through the delivery of exceptional product quality and service, and prudent management of people, technology and processes.

I have proven ability to manage budgets in excess of USD6 million; align technology strategy with corporate strategy; set business and group goals; and lead management teams to achieve project goals and exceed client expectations.

CORE COMPETENCIES

Strategic Planning & Direction, Policy Development, Organizational re-engineering, Project Management, Services Management & SLA's, Root Cause Analysis, IT Governance (including for public service and Donor funded projects), Information System Security, Report Preparation & Presentation, Business Process Reengineering, Risk management & Quality Assurance, Budget Administration, Change Management, Client and Vendor Relations, User Requirements Consulting, Performance management, Research & Development, vast knowledge of automated financial systems, SAP ERP, service delivery software. IT Consulting, Public Service procurement of ICT assets.

Personal Attributes:

- · Highly motivated, team building, and mentoring and motivation skills
- · Reliable, diligent, trustworthy, impeccable high personal integrity,
- Inter-personal skills, networking capabilities, negotiation skills,
- High resilience (patience, tolerance, and working under pressure),
- courage to take unpopular stand

SIGNIFICANT ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Headed a team which successfully negotiated a maintenance contract for a World bank funded Euros 6.5Million IT Systems implementation at Jomo Kenyatta International Airport in 2015.
- Improved service delivery and monitoring through implementation of an automated service desk system with real-time SLA monitoring and reporting, and multi-level escalations for the entire Kenya Airports Authority enterprise (Head Office and 12 airports) in 2014.
- Project Managed SAP ERP implementation for Kenya Airports Authority, across Head Office and 12 airports, airstrips in June 2011 – Apr 2013. Project worth USD 6M+.

- Set up a PMO office from scratch, including a secretariat, which was used by the Steering committee and project implementation teams for the KAA Project Eagle ERP implementation.
- Stopped the renewal of an enterprise maintenance agreement because my employer was not accruing the desired benefits. Reviewed and improved the requisite internal capacity through recruitment of systems administrators before resuming the contract.
- Nominated Silensec Best IT Manager 2010. Silensec is an international IT Security Training and Consultancy firm
- Recommended the termination of a major contract to international contractor on non-performance, which was approved.
- Project managed the procurement and deployment of ATM machines for Diamond Trust Bank (DTB) in Uganda, and Tanzania and their integration to Pesa Point Payment Switching Network. (Aug Oct 2007)
- Coordinated the participation of Fintech International in AITEC conference in banking systems. (2006).
- Initiated strategic review of Fintech International company operations, which the Directors adopted my proposal for business re-engineering. (2006).
- Project managed the integration of MicroBanker to Coop Switch Payment Switching Network for Afya SACCO and Bandari SACCO. (2002 2005).
- Implemented online, real-time DR setup for Credit Bank Ltd and Eurafrican Bank Ltd, to back up Live database to a DR server in another town, effectively enhancing the BCP. (2002).
- Contracted to maintain the banking system for Family Finance Building Society as a private consultant. (1998).
- Designed, developed, implemented and maintained a banking/financial system for Credit Bank Ltd and Family Finance Building Society. (1992 - 1995)
- Received commendations for outstanding year-end support at Credit Kenya Ltd and was nominated the Best Employee Software, Division in my first year of employment at Business Machines (K) Ltd.

EMPLOYMENT

KENYA AIRPORTS AUTHORITY (KAA)

Feb 2012 - Present

(KAA is a public institution created by an Act of Parliament and mandated to develop and manage all aerodromes in Kenya)

ICT Manager, Service Management

• Provide ICT Service leadership for highly available and reliable automated business systems

KENYA AIRPORTS AUTHORITY

June 2011 - April 2013

Project Manager, SAP ERP Implementation

• Project manage implementation of SAP ERP ECC 6.0 for Kenya Airports Authority (All branches)

KENYA AIRPORTS AUTHORITY

Sept 2010 - Jan 2012

Ag. General Manager, ICT

 Provide executive management of the ICT department, executing the full mandate of policy, strategy, leadership, governance

KENYA AIRPORTS AUTHORITY

Oct 2007 - Sept 2010

ICT Services Development Manager

• Leadership of the development and maintenance of various business automation including network infrastructure, Server rooms, collaboration services, engineering SW, etc

DIAMOND TRUST BANK

Aug 2007 - Oct 2007

Manager, Regional ICT Projects

• Managed the acquisition and implementation of business automation products and services in Tanzania and Uganda

FINTECH INTERNATIONAL

2006 - 2007

Business Development Manager

 Grow the IT service integration and support business while providing support team leadership and project management

FINTECH INTERNATIONAL

2001 - 2006

ESA Services Manager

Manage the Enterprise Systems Applications (ESA) Services unit, leading a team of 10 in the
development and support of mission critical banking, financial and integrated systems for customers
across the Eastern Africa region, with fortnightly SLA reporting to our principal in India.

FINTECH INTERNATIONAL

1998 -2001

Systems Consultant

 Member of the Banking Systems Division providing implementation and support services for mission critical banking, financial and integrated systems for customers across the Eastern Africa region, with fortnightly SLA reporting to our principal in India.

PRIVATE CONSULTANCY

Feb 1998 - June 1998

Systems Consultant

Provided consultancy services to various clients in the areas of systems upgrade and support, HW
acquisition, training, report generation.

BUSINESS MACHINES LIMITED (BML)

1996 -1997

Deputy Software Manager

 Lead and supervise the sales, implementation and service provision of financial/accounting and other business applications for various clients in Kenya. Prepare work plans and manage the divisional budget.

BUSINESS MACHINES LIMITED (BML)

1995 - 1996

Senior Systems Analyst

• Design and development of banking application for two financial institutions in Kenya. Implementation and support of banking and accounting software for various clients in Kenya.

BUSINESS MACHINES LIMITED (BML)

1990 -1995

Project Leader

• Applications enhancement, installations, training and support to various clients in Kenya.

BUSINESS MACHINES LIMITED (BML)

1989 -1990

Programmer

Applications support and enhancement, and in-house payroll support.

EDUCATION

2009	UNIVERSITY OF NAIROBI Master of Business Administration (MBA) Major: Accounting and Finance
1991	KENYA INSTITUTE OF MANAGEMENT Diploma in Management (completed coursework)
1988	UNIVERSITY OF NAIROBI Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.) Major: Mathematics and Computer Science

PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS AND CERTIFICATIONS

KENYA SCHOOL OF GOVERNMENT Supervisory Management Course

KENYA BUREAU OF STANDARDS (KEBS)

Active Member of Kenya Bureau of Standards (KEBS) Technical Committee on Electronic Cards, Personal Identification and Biometrics

Active Member of Kenya Bureau of Standards (KEBS) Technical Committee on SW Engineering, IT Service Management & IT Governance

COMPUTER SOCIETY OF KENYA (CSK)
Fellow of the Computer Society of Kenya (FCSK)

KENYA AIRPORTS AUTHORITY (KAA)

Member of the Tender Committee

PRINCE2 (Practitioner) Certification
ITIL Certification
SAP Certified Associate in Business Foundation and Integration
SCO Master ACE in UNIX